<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<metadata xml:lang="en">
<dataIdInfo>
<idCitation>
<resTitle>Deep geothermal potential areas in the UK, version 2</resTitle>
</idCitation>
<searchKeys>
<keyword>Deep geothermal</keyword>
</searchKeys>
<idPurp>This shapefile shows polygons where there is favourable geology for deep geothermal exploration in the UK and for the sedimentary basins, the areas have been considered in more detailed geothermal studies. </idPurp>
<idAbs>&lt;DIV STYLE="text-align:Left;"&gt;&lt;DIV&gt;&lt;DIV&gt;&lt;UL STYLE="margin:0 0 0 0;padding:0 0 0 0;"&gt;&lt;LI&gt;&lt;P STYLE="text-align:Justify;margin:0 0 0 0;"&gt;&lt;SPAN STYLE="font-size:9pt"&gt;This shapefile shows polygons where there is favourable geology for deep geothermal exploration in the UK &lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;and&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;SPAN STYLE="font-size:9pt"&gt; for the sedimentary basins, the areas have been considered in more detailed geothermal studies. &lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;/LI&gt;&lt;LI&gt;&lt;P STYLE="text-align:Justify;margin:0 0 0 0;"&gt;&lt;SPAN STYLE="font-size:9pt"&gt;Known areas of sedimentary basins or productive aquifers &lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;have been excluded&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;SPAN STYLE="font-size:9pt"&gt;, where they have not yet been evaluated for geothermal potential at any level of detail. &lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;/LI&gt;&lt;LI&gt;&lt;P STYLE="text-align:Justify;margin:0 0 0 0;"&gt;&lt;SPAN STYLE="font-weight:bold;font-size:9pt"&gt;The areas included are the whole sedimentary basin extents, or extents of granitic intrusions, as opposed to the smaller areas with heat-in-place or proved, recoverable resources over certain temperatures and depths&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;SPAN STYLE="font-size:9pt"&gt;. &lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;/LI&gt;&lt;LI&gt;&lt;P STYLE="text-align:Justify;margin:0 0 0 0;"&gt;&lt;SPAN STYLE="font-size:9pt"&gt;Coordinate Reference System is British National Grid. Northern Ireland data is also presented in British National Grid because of the UK extent of the information. &lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;/LI&gt;&lt;LI&gt;&lt;P STYLE="text-align:Justify;margin:0 0 0 0;"&gt;&lt;SPAN STYLE="font-size:9pt"&gt;Additional columns are as required to be supplied for inclusion in the GSEU project (&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;A href="https://www.geologicalservice.eu/" STYLE="text-decoration:underline;"&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;https://www.geologicalservice.eu/&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/A&gt;&lt;SPAN STYLE="font-size:9pt"&gt;). These include a ‘Geothermal Play Code’, ‘Geothermal Play Type’ ‘Plate Tectonic Setting’ ‘Geologic Habitat’ and ‘Geological Controls’ fields following the classification scheme of Moeck, I. S. (2014, Catalog of geothermal play types based on geologic controls. Renewable and Sustainable Energy Reviews, 37, 867-882). &lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;/LI&gt;&lt;LI&gt;&lt;P STYLE="text-align:Justify;margin:0 0 0 0;"&gt;&lt;SPAN STYLE="font-size:9pt"&gt;Additional fields have been added for BGS for classification, colouring up.&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;/LI&gt;&lt;/UL&gt;&lt;/DIV&gt;&lt;/DIV&gt;&lt;/DIV&gt;</idAbs>
<idCredit>Polygons were created by BGS using information from the following sources:
Rollin, K. E., G. A. Kirby, and W. J. Rowley. Atlas of geothermal resources in Europe: UK revision. British Geological Survey, Regional Geophysics Group, 1995.
As incorporated in Busby 2013 (https://doi.org/10.1007/s10040-013-1054-4 ), from BGS extent maps and extended northwards in 2024 using BGS DIGMAP 50k data for the Fell Sandstone extent in Northumberland.
BGS Bedrock Geology 625K V5, BGS Bedrock Geology 50K V8
BGS Tectonic Map of Britain, Ireland and adjacent areas. 1:1,500,00 series. 1996. 
Raine and Reay, 2021 Geothermal energy potential in Northern Ireland: summary and recommendations for the Geothermal Advisory Committee https://nora.nerc.ac.uk/id/eprint/531393/  Some stratigraphical information has been included but this needs to be updated. 
Kearsey et al. 2024 Midland Valley of Scotland geothermal aquifer modelling study – BGS report in preparation OR/24/030, though the extent shown is BGS mapped extent of Carboniferous and Upper Devonian strata. 
Extended the Permo-Trias southwards in the East Yorkshire-Lincolnshire area from Newell, A. 2023 The Sherwood Sandstone and Bacton groups of the East Midlands Shelf – an onshore to offshore correlation using outcrop evidence and geophysical logs. Nottingham, UK, British Geological Survey, 40pp. (OR/23/051). https://nora.nerc.ac.uk/id/eprint/536918/ 
For selected granites, extents from BGS 625k and BGS tectonic map, names as used in McCay and Younger 2017 (https://doi.org/10.1144/sjg2016-008) and in Gillespie et al. 2013 (BGS for Scottish Government https://www.gov.scot/publications/study-potential-deep-geothermal-energy-scotland-volume-2/pages/10/)  Note that some granites are outcrop extent only, some are concealed only (from geophysics and borehole penetrations) and some are both outcrop and concealed. 
Carboniferous limestone extent, northern province is a extent of study polygon, southern province are mapped extent of subcropping basins, from Jones et al. 2023. Deep geothermal resource assessment of early carboniferous limestones for Central and Southern Great Britain, Geothermics, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.geothermics.2023.102649 
</idCredit>
<resConst>
<Consts>
<useLimit>&lt;DIV STYLE="text-align:Left;"&gt;&lt;DIV&gt;&lt;DIV&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;OGL&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;/DIV&gt;&lt;/DIV&gt;&lt;/DIV&gt;</useLimit>
</Consts>
</resConst>
</dataIdInfo>
<mdHrLv>
<ScopeCd value="005">
</ScopeCd>
</mdHrLv>
</metadata>
